I'm E. F. Lavert Miller.
Welcome to The Scholars, a television interview series
that explores contemporary scholarship.
We hope to engage and challenge your thinking
on a broad range of topics.
You'll meet a diverse group of scholars
who are investigating and thinking about a complex
and changing world.
John Carriacou is the author of The Reluctant Spy,
My Secret Life in the CIA's War on Terror.
He worked at the Central Intelligence Agency
from 1990 to 2004.
He's currently an associate fellow
with the Institute for Policy Studies.
Welcome to The Scholars, John.
Thanks very much for having me.
You know, I want to go back to what you described
in your book, Reluctant Spy,
as a key moment in terms of the change of life.
November 4th, 1979.
What happened on that day?
That was the day that Iranian students
overtook the American Embassy
and took dozens of our diplomats hostage.
I never even really thought much about the Middle East.
I was 15 years old when it happened.
I thought I wanted to be a dentist when I grew up.
But the hostage taking in Iran
opened up this whole new world for me in the Middle East,
and I developed a fascination with the Middle East
that I carried through college.
I got a degree in Middle Eastern studies,
and it really did change the course of my life.
You know, when a young person is coming out of college,
they went, okay, what's next, okay?
Right.
You've written a book about,
One Never Leaves a CIA, okay?
Why did you join the CIA?
My family is relatively new in the United States.
My father's parents came here in 1931,
and my mother's parents in 1934.
And my grandparents always instilled in us the idea
that we were so lucky to be in this country.
We were so fortunate for the opportunities
that we had been given for work, for education,
most of all, that we needed to give back to the country.
And so public service was always a big deal in our house
from volunteering when I was young
to going into the public sector as an adult.
It was always strongly encouraged.
Now, you develop skills
that I guess people would probably admire.
You become an analyst.
I mean, what does that mean, and what did you do?
That was the best job in the world.
It's the best job I've ever had.
And in fact, even after I left the CIA,
I've compared every subsequent job to that one,
and none of them compare.
To put it succinctly, you think the big thoughts.
You go onto your computer every morning when you get to work
and you start reading cable traffic.
This is reports from the State Department.
And you're a news junkie.
I'm a news junkie.
And this was the real inside story.
So you get State Department reports,
you get CIA reports, NSA, lots and lots of press reports.
Sometimes cables from the Defense Department or the FBI.
And you get to see what happened overnight
in the part of the world that you're covering.
And once you get all this information,
you use your own intelligence to put it all together
to write it in a cogent and tight form
that the CIA teaches you.
And you send those papers to the President,
the Vice President, the Secretaries of State and Defense
and the National Security Advisor.
And when you're 23, 24, 25 years old,
there's nothing headier than sending a paper to the White House
and then having it come back to you
where the President has scribbled comments
in the market.
Let me scribble some comments right here.
So you're taking all this information
from here and there and there.
My question now is, what is your knowledge of history?
You know, that's really a key.
And that's why an analytic job at the CIA
is not for everybody.
Because you really have to be a student of history.
You know the old saying that those who don't know history
are doomed to repeat it.
It's your job to make sure that the policymaker doesn't repeat it.
And so you really have to be a subject matter expert.
Let me mention this because I've seen some books
that have come out about the CIA.
And what happens is sometime in terms of a staff person
working one part of the world has moved over
to another part of the world and might be making policy
with no knowledge of the history of a particular country.
Is that still happening?
That happens every day in our government.
See, this is a problem not specific to the CIA
but really all over our foreign policy
and national security policy apparatus.
You can be the world's greatest expert
on a given topic in the CIA.
But an elected official who's tasked with making policy
can choose to just ignore whatever it is you have to say.
Don't forget, a lot of our politicians think
that they're always the smartest people in the room.
And most of the time, frankly, they're not.
Right.
It's the person who lost an election.
That's right.
They're the most arrogant people in the room.
And oftentimes, they're not willing to take advice.
And the advice, at least that's
coming from the CIA's analytic unit,
the Directorate of Intelligence,
is very well thought out and coordinated advice.
Let's talk about another discipline.
So I mentioned history.
What about being an analyst at CIA?
Where does philosophy and ethics come into play,
in terms of policy?
That's a great question.
This was a problem that I had with the CIA
from the very beginning.
Ethics is not taught at the CIA.
It's not stressed.
It's not even touched upon.
And you really have to fall back
on your own personal ethics, your own personal morality,
to guide the course of your career.
That's less important on the analytic side
than it is on the operational side.
But this is something that's very sorely lacking in the CIA.
You know, when we look at the CIA,
and we talked a minute ago about
how your life was changed back in 79,
what happens to the CIA after 9-11?
Oh boy.
Absolutely everything changed after 9-11.
I had switched from analysis to operations in 1998.
So I was already in operations
when the September 11th attacks happened.
But, you know, Ethel Burke,
it's as though we lost our way after September 11th.
We were so obsessed with capturing or killing
Osama bin Laden and with disrupting a future attack
that we threw whatever ethics,
whatever morality we had out the window.
We instituted a torture program, for example.
As a government, we developed a drone program
that's used to assassinate people around the world.
These are things that we wouldn't have dreamt of doing
pre 9-11, but the rules all seemed to change.
Well, you know, when people say that, okay,
I go back to the speech that George Bush
gave to Congress after 9-11.
And it seems in that speech,
you get this sort of mandate of the world has changed
and now we will sit down and work with people
that we may not wanna work with, but the world has changed.
And we see this as if we become offensive
in our foreign policy.
We've certainly become police in our foreign policy.
We've offended allies.
You'll recall during the Bush administration,
the talk, I think it was from Secretary of Defense
Rumsfeld about old Europe versus new Europe
and that the new Europeans were with us
and the old Europeans could lump it if they didn't like it.
We became increasingly comfortable in a unipolar world
which I think was wrong headed
and I think offended other countries
that might have been willing to work with us otherwise.
And this whole thing,
our entire national security structure changed
to the point where,
well really for most of the Bush administration,
I had never seen an administration that worked so hard
to not use diplomacy as the Bush administration.
I was very confident when President Obama was elected
because I thought finally,
we're gonna have some realpolitik
and we're gonna have people who think about this kind
of thing and people who use diplomacy,
we're gonna have peace talks.
Let's go back to Jimi Carter's administration.
Well you might recall,
human rights became very important.
In fact, that's when the State Department started writing
at the annual Human Rights Report was under President Carter.
And some people felt that Carter was a weak president.
And some people felt that he was compromising
in areas that he should not have compromised,
Nicaragua being one.
How do we look at that now?
I think that historians will tell you
that Carter was right.
I think that historians will say
that we grossly underestimated Jimmy Carter as president.
The fact that he's the best former president
we've ever had aside,
he guided very difficult relations with Pakistan
from 1977 to 1981.
This was a time when the Soviets had invaded Afghanistan
and we were really reliant on the Pakistani government
at a time of its own turmoil to help us craft the policy.
It was Jimmy Carter that led that policy.
We could easily have gone to war with Iran
after the hostage crisis.
And while Carter tried to rescue the hostages,
it failed of course.
But we could easily have invaded that country
to try to win the freedom of our hostages
or more importantly to punish the Iranian government
for taking them in the first place.
And we didn't.
Well let's look at the big issue here
that we might see in terms of the change.
And that is we're moving from a cold war mentality
into this new war against terrorism.
How does the battle against communism
now compare to the battle against terrorism?
Oh the battle against communism was much, much easier
for two reasons.
First of all, you knew who your enemy was.
And secondly, you knew that you could sit across
the table from your enemy and negotiate
no matter how difficult the issue was.
And that's not the world we live in today.
What is the world we live in today?
The world we live in today is that we refuse
to negotiate even if the other side wants to.
It's our policy that we don't.
We are much more comfortable using armed drones.
And we're more comfortable using combat troops
to express our foreign policy.
You mentioned Runsville previously.
I remember Runsville made a statement a number of years ago
that there would be no need to place a US soldier
in harm's way because of the emphasis
on robotic in terms of drones.
And it seems as if we've passed that point.
We've passed it to the point where we're murdering
even American citizens overseas.
American citizens who have not been charged with a crime.
American citizens who have not had the right
to confront their accusers in a court of law.
And in at least two cases,
American citizens who were wrongly targeted.
And then we don't even issue so much
as an apology for those attacks.
Let's talk about some definitions here.
We hear often the word terrorism being used.
How is that defined?
I would define terrorism as any act meant
to instill terror in a broader audience.
And I think that both the Bush and Obama administrations
have defined it differently.
They would define it as any act in and of itself
that poses a threat to the security of the United States.
Period.
I was reading your book and I got on page 135 and 136.
You outlined some of the techniques.
I couldn't even get through reading some of them.
And seeing this if, for example,
let it for the definition that you just gave up with,
I wouldn't want to subject anybody to this.
No.
No, what you're talking about is the torture techniques
that we use to get prisoners to.
I mentioned like two or three of them.
There are three that are really, I think horrific.
The one that's garnered the most press is waterboarding.
Where a person is laid on a gurney
with the feet slightly elevated.
His face is covered with some sort of material burlap,
cloth, whatever.
And then water is poured on his face.
It instills a sense of drowning,
which is very painful because your body reacts to it.
Your body contorts, your abdominal muscles tense up
and you really do feel like you're drowning.
But there are a couple of others
that I always thought were worse than waterboarding.
One is what's called the cold cell,
where a prison cell is chilled to about 50 degrees.
A prisoner is stripped naked.
He's thrown in the cell
and then ice water is thrown on him every hour or so.
We had a prisoner in Afghanistan
by the name of Hassan Gul
who did not survive that technique
and died during the night because of the cold.
There's a third one and that is sleep deprivation.
And I don't mean keeping a prisoner awake
for a night, two nights, even three nights.
I'm talking about keeping a prisoner awake
for two weeks at a time
where they're chained to an eye bolt in the ceiling
so they can't lay down,
they can't really even kneel down or crouch down,
and they can't hang from the eye bolt
because it's so painful after a period of time.
We want to describe, I remember this goes back
to Norieger and they were playing music constantly.
Constantly.
Is that would be a form of torture also?
I think it is.
It's weeks on end with all the lights on
and hard rock blasting at you into your cell.
You just can't sleep, you can't rest.
And what that does is it makes a person hallucinate.
In one case, we know that a prisoner lost his mind
to the point where he's not able
to participate in his own defense.
What role does racism play in torture?
Oh, I think that racism plays
a very large role in torture.
You know, there's this famous experiment,
the Stanford Prison Experiment,
where a group of Stanford psychology graduate students
were divided into groups.
Some were gonna play the role of prisoners
and some of prison guards.
People started to go crazy after only 36 hours
and the experiment was canceled, rather,
in its entirety after only six days.
And it's because people really did adopt
the idea that they were better than others.
We see this in American prisons every day
and I can tell you that from firsthand experience.
Talk about that, what did you do?
Sure, I spent two years in prison, 23 months in prison.
I was charged with three counts of espionage,
one count of violating the Intelligence Identities
Protection Act and one count of making a false statement
because I went on ABC News in 2007
and I told the whole country, the whole world,
that we were torturing prisoners,
that torture was official U.S. government policy
and that the president had signed that policy
and was lying to us when he looked into the camera
and said, we do not torture, I knew that that was a lie
and I said so on national news.
You're very active now, you're at the Institute
of Apology Study, you're really concerned
about prison reform and I was wondering
whether when we talk about prison reform,
might we be talking about three things.
One, the actual lawyers themselves,
to the criminal justice system
and then the actual conditions in the prison.
Oh yes, first of all, our entire prison system
is based on racism.
Look at disparities in sentencing,
just as one quick example.
On average, sentences for crimes related to crack
are 10 times longer than sentences
for crimes related to powdered cocaine.
Okay, it's all cocaine, it's all the same drug,
but crack is a black man's drug
and powdered coke is a white man's drug
and so if I'm gonna get two years
because I'm selling a little bit of coke on the side,
you're gonna get 20 years
for selling a little bit of crack on the side.
That's just inherent systemic racism.
I'll give this president credit,
he's trying to do something to correct those disparities
but we've got an entire generation
of young African-American men
who's defining event in the course of their lives.
Who's lives are being destroyed.
Yeah, it's prison and their lives are destroyed.
You do 20 years in prison
for having a little bit of crack.
How do you rebuild from that?
Our cities aren't equipped to help people rebuild from that.
And we also, within the prison,
we don't hear terms like rehabilitation.
Oh, never.
There's no such thing as correction.
There's no such thing as rehabilitation.
Time was as recently as the early 1980s
where you could go to prison and get a college education.
You could go to prison and learn a skill.
You could become a plumber or an electrician or a mechanic
or any number of different things, no longer.
There's no money for it
because we're spending the money
on incarcerating these vast numbers of people.
There's no money left over for education.
What country has the more humane prison system?
I was looking at this asset of tragedy in Norway
where it seemed as if a person was treated completely different
even though the crime was correct.
You took the words right out of my mouth.
I think Norway probably has
the most progressive prison system in the world.
Iceland is similarly progressive.
These are all countries with no black people.
Yeah, right.
You're right.
They're no people of color.
Maybe the occasional Muslim immigrant and that's about it.
But in those countries, when you get a sentence
of life, what that means is 17 years.
So at the end of 17 years, you're gonna be released.
But when you're released, you've earned a college degree
and you've learned a skill
and you've undergone psychiatric or psychological counseling
and you're ready to reintegrate into society.
Here, you get nothing except a GED.
They will assign another prisoner to tutor you
so you can get your GED.
But let's say you have your GED
or you already have a high school education.
You get out after doing your time
and they've not taught you anything.
You've earned no money.
I worked a regular job.
I worked every day and I made a dollar eight a month.
So everybody else is making what I'm making.
So you work and work and work
and you're in prison for 10 years or 20 years.
You're making a buck a month.
You can't leave with anything to get your life started.
You've not learned a skill.
You have no counseling.
There's no job training.
There's nobody helping to place you in a position.
There's no mental health counseling.
And so you have a lot of very angry, undereducated,
unemployable felons hitting the street.
Well, they're gonna end up doing
the only thing that they know how to do
and that is to go back on the streets
and sell drugs to make money to support their families.
Let me mention something in terms of you
responding to the prisons
but also I want to bring it back to terrorism.
And that's privatization.
Yes.
Where you look up that in some of these cases,
it is not you as military people doing the torturing,
but it's a private contractor.
And we also went to the thing where it seems
as if there was money made in terms of building prisons.
I remember going out to one time to Youngstone, Ohio.
One of the worst.
And at the same time,
if you take away that prison industry,
here is a city that because of the economy,
it's going bankrupt.
That's all they have.
So talk about this privatization in prison reform.
I've actually, from a small town, very, very near Youngstone.
You walk to Youngstone, right in a pinch.
Newcastle, Pennsylvania.
You're absolutely right about private prisons.
This was a grave policy error that we made in the 1980s
to allow prisons to be privatized.
So we have private companies
like the Corrections Corporation of America
and they build prisons around the country,
the one you mentioned being one of the most prominent
in Youngstone, Ohio.
But these companies, first of all,
don't have an incentive to provide anything to prisoners.
No education.
What about the profit motor?
It's all about the profits.
And how do they make their profits?
They're paid a certain amount of money per prisoner per year
to house both federal and state prisoners.
Whatever they don't spend on that prisoner,
they get to keep.
So they don't want to spend the money on medication
or on a doctor to oversee the health of prisoners,
despite the fact that diseases like tuberculosis
and HIV and...
And also the impact on older prisoners.
Especially on older prisoners.
Right.
And hepatitis are rampant.
And they don't want to spend the money on education
or counseling or training
because whatever they don't spend,
they can send back to their shareholders
or put in their own pockets.
And so...
Doctor, how do you reform that?
How do you break these type of cycles?
Honestly, I think there are several things
that have to be done.
First of all, I don't think we should have
private prisons in this country.
Nothing good comes out of a private prison.
One of my cellmates, I'll just tell you a small anecdote,
one of my cellmates spent just two weeks
in a private prison in Virginia
called the Orange County Transportation Center.
220 male inmates, one toilet, the seat was broken,
one TV, and there was a fist fight every hour
with the winner determining what show to watch.
That's inhumane.
That's not the way we should be treating people
in our country.
But again, it's all about that profit motive.
So first of all,
I don't think we should have private prisons
in this country.
Secondly, overcrowding is absolutely criminal.
And overcrowding leads to the spread of disease,
it leads to violence,
and it's just simply too expensive.
Let me connect this to something else
which we've been talking about.
Sure.
How does these conditions affect our national security?
Wow.
Well, I think,
and this may be a little bit controversial,
but I think that some of the policies
that we have in our prisons amount to torture.
For example, I think that solitary confinement
is a form of torture.
There's one man in particular
in the Angola State Penitentiary in Louisiana
who's been in solitary confinement for 44 years.
He has not had human interaction in 44 years.
Well, a lot of these folks
eventually are gonna get out.
And when they get out, they're gonna be crazy
and they're gonna be violent.
And that destabilizes our communities.
And when our communities are destabilized,
the country is destabilized.
Yeah, when you say that,
we've gone through a number of incidents,
but in terms of police brutality,
when you look at a certain percentage,
some of the individuals
have suffered some form of mental illness.
Absolutely.
And I think that's the thing in terms of,
you arrive on a scene
and someone's acting in a certain way and they're black.
Well, what happens,
no one knows whether that person lack medication,
counseling or whatever, you just see the result.
Yeah, and what happens more often than not,
unfortunately, is the police just open fire.
Right.
Let me ask you this when you're getting in our show.
Using your skills as an analyst,
what human rights and private issues
should we be concerned about in the next 10 years?
Well, we could write a book about it.
I'll come back for another program.
Privacy is absolutely critically important right now
to the American people.
And it's because we've essentially lost our privacy
without even so much as a debate.
We really had to.
Let me ask you this.
You work for the CIA.
Hey, I mean,
weren't you concerned about people's privacy?
I mean, you know.
Well, the CIA is focused on foreign intelligence collectively.
And since the reforms of the church committee in 1975,
76, I wasn't concerned.
I am now.
I'm talking about privacy of people overseas though.
Well, you're right.
I want to spy on people overseas.
Don't forget, you know, and I say this all the time,
that progressives are patriots too.
And I wanted to do everything I could
to protect the American people.
So I want to bring you back to a question I asked you earlier.
These philosophical ethical issues.
Yes.
It's not like gravity is different over there than here.
I mean, spying is spying, isn't it?
Yes, spying is spying.
And certainly, most of our allies spy on us
just like we spy on them.
So what do you see as being a key issue
in the next couple of years, in turn?
I think the key issue is our intelligence community
organization is spying on us.
Spying on American citizens.
For example, NSA.
Not only is it illegal for NSA to spy on American citizens,
but it's in NSA's charter from its creation
that it's not permitted to spy on American citizens.
Well, we would have had no idea
that NSA was spying on us had Ed Snowden not
gone public with his revelations.
How do you view Snowden?
I think Ed Snowden's a national hero.
I really do.
He is the very definition of a whistleblower, Ethelbert.
He revealed evidence of waste, fraud, abuse, or illegality.
And to me, that makes him a hero, not a criminal.
And when we look at how a person should
read your book, The Reluctant Spy,
should we read it reluctantly?
I call myself a reluctant spy for a couple of reasons.
One, I enjoyed analysis very much.
I was reluctant to get into operations.
But I did, and I enjoyed it, and I was good at it.
I was reluctant to allow my marriage
to break up because of my CIA work.
And that's exactly what happened.
I go into some detail about that.
And I was reluctant to the point of being unwilling
to engage in what I believed to be war crimes or crimes
against humanity when the CIA began violating
the human rights of those that we were capturing.
Well, John, I'm glad I captured you for the show,
and I'll let you go.
But I want to thank you in terms of being my guest here.
Thanks for joining me on The Scholars.
Thank you for watching.
I'm Ethelbert Miller.